<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>BMS's Blog</title><link href="http://brianstempin.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://brianstempin.com/feeds/general-work-stuff.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://brianstempin.com/</id><updated>2015-12-21T20:27:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>JetBrians DataGrip Review</title><link href="http://brianstempin.com/2015/12/21/jetbrains-datagrip-review/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-21T20:27:00-05:00</updated><author><name>bstempi</name></author><id>tag:brianstempin.com,2015-12-21:2015/12/21/jetbrains-datagrip-review/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently, &lt;a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/"&gt;JetBrains&lt;/a&gt; released a new product called &lt;a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/datagrip/"&gt;DataGrip&lt;/a&gt;.  It's basically IntelliJ for databases, and so far, I love it!  Granted:  I'm biased.  I do all of my Java and Python development using IntelliJ and PyCharm, respectively.  That being said, I think that even if I were still using some other IDE on a day-to-day basis, DataGrip would still be at the top of my list as a general database access and manipulation tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Making Quick Data Analysis Quicker&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know about you, but I really hate the &lt;code&gt;sqlite&lt;/code&gt; command line tool.  It lacks autocomplete and is really picky.  &lt;code&gt;sqlite&lt;/code&gt;, however, is a really handy tool for doing some quick analysis of CSVs or TSVs, so I end up using it quite a bit.  In my few uses of DataGrip, I used it instead of the &lt;code&gt;sqlite&lt;/code&gt; command line client to query databases that I had already built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Observation One: Adding a New Data Source Was Kind of Confusing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By default, DG doesn't come with any (many?  I'm not sure) of the drivers installed!  This was really confusing the first time I tried to add a data source.  To DG's credit:  if you go to the driver screen, you can click a download link that will get and install the driver for you.  I understand that licensing issues sometimes prevent vendors from including libraries such as these in their products.  What I don't get, however, is why they didn't take this ease-of-installation feature a step further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot showing the drivers screen" src="http://brianstempin.com/images/download-driver-screenshot.png" title="Screenshot showing the drivers screen. WTF, JetBrains?!" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If they detect that this is the firs time that I've run this product, why not offer to download them all for me?  If JetBrains is ok giving me a download and installation facility, then they should present it to me up-front so that I can download all of the drivers I need and never think of it again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Observation Two:  The Autocomplete is Really Nice&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that autocomplete has been around forever, but there's something especially nice about this one.  It's snappy.  Very snappy.  Exceptionally snappy.  Perhaps this might change once I throw larger schemas at it, but it's snappy enough to remind me of why I left &lt;a href="http://www.eclipse.org/"&gt;Eclipse&lt;/a&gt;-land in the first place and to be glad to see JetBrains releasing new tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Observation Three:  Exporting Results is a Breeze&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I'm doing a quick or one-off analysis, I usually want to export the results so that I can chart it or sent it to a colleague.  The export tools are wonderful.  There aren't a ton of formats that you can export into, but the ones that I would expect were present.  You can also "export to clipboard," allowing you to copy-paste results easily.  For someone that's running exploratory queries that have relatively small result sets, this is pretty awesome.  It allows me to easily put my output into a web page (as JSON or CSV) for charting (in my case, I use &lt;a href="http://nvd3.org/"&gt;NVD3&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Overall&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DataGrip is a pretty cool tool.  Lately I haven't had a go-to tool for connecting to and running SQL queries.  This just became "it" for me.  I'm curious to see what it does on larger queries with larger result sets.  I'm sure the tool has it's limits, but from what I've seen, I'm confident they're pretty sane and reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm looking forward to find ways to leverage DG to chart and graph data as quickly as I can query it.  Good job, JetBrains!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="tools"></category><category term="database"></category></entry><entry><title>ZOMG, Apache Camel is Awesome!</title><link href="http://brianstempin.com/2013/07/07/zomg-apache-camel-is-awesome/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-07-07T22:12:00-04:00</updated><author><name>bstempi</name></author><id>tag:brianstempin.com,2013-07-07:2013/07/07/zomg-apache-camel-is-awesome/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;At the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.coldlight.com/"&gt;work place&lt;/a&gt;, I've had to do a lot
of integration work on my current project. &amp;nbsp;Instead of trying to tie
everything together on my own, someone recommended taking a look at
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://camel.apache.org/"&gt;Apache Camel&lt;/a&gt;. &amp;nbsp;Man, did that have a
drastically good effect on my project!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="well-what-is-it"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Well, What is it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's an integration framework written in Java. &amp;nbsp;In short, it's meant to
make the act of integrating systems together easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="enough-of-the-jibberish-wtfsck-is-an-integration-framework"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Enough of the Jibberish -- WTFsck() is an Integration Framework?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah, that line wouldn't have made much sense to me, either, before
reading the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.amazon.com/Camel-Action-Claus-Ibsen/dp/1935182366/"&gt;Camel
book&lt;/a&gt;.
&amp;nbsp;It's probably best to refer to an example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's say you have some really annoying manual process that you use to
tie together two systems. &amp;nbsp;I had a previous employer who would create
ISO images and then had to manually upload them to a partner's site so
that they could mass-produce optical media from said image. &amp;nbsp;Some
person, who was not a seasoned FTP user (nor wanted to be) had to have a
set of credentials, access to the ISO, and had to babysit the upload.
&amp;nbsp;They also had the ability to break the transfer via FTP options. &amp;nbsp;In
this case, the partner needed us to use a specific set of options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is something that Camel could do easily. &amp;nbsp;Users create &amp;quot;routes&amp;quot; to
describe processes like the one above. &amp;nbsp;These routes can be described in
Java, XML, or one of the many DSLs (domain specific languages) that are
included. &amp;nbsp;Here's an example route in XML that could satisfy the above
problem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
&amp;lt;route id=&amp;quot;publishIso&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;from uri=&amp;quot;file://path/to/iso/finished.iso&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;to uri=&amp;quot;ftp://user&amp;#64;ftp.partner.com/path/to/publish/duplicateMe.iso?password=superSecret&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/route&amp;gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This route can be embedded inside of a Spring config file. To launch the
route, the developer would just have to start a Spring context. This
would start Camel, which would read the XML file. It would then sit
there and scan the /path/to/iso/ directory for a filed named
finished.iso every 500ms (by default, as of the time of this writing).
When it finds the file, it will upload it to the specified FTP site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simple, eh? All that from a little bit of XML and starting a Spring
context (all of less than 6 lines of code in Java).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="go-on"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Go on...&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, as I stated, you can embed this into a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://camel.apache.org/spring.html"&gt;Spring
configuration&lt;/a&gt; file. Upon
starting the context, Camel will start. You can also describe routes
using the&amp;nbsp;Java &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://camel.apache.org/dsl.html"&gt;DSL&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
from(&amp;quot;file://path/to/iso/finished.iso&amp;quot;)
    .to(&amp;quot;ftp://user&amp;#64;ftp.partner.com/path/to/publish/duplicateMe.iso?password=superSecret&amp;quot;);
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;quot;from&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;to&amp;quot; are described as
&amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://camel.apache.org/endpoint.html"&gt;Endpoints&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; in Camel.
&amp;nbsp;Endpoints are created by
&amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://camel.apache.org/component.html"&gt;Components&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;quot; &amp;nbsp;This simple
route demonstrates the File2 and FTP Components being used to generate
two Endpoints. &amp;nbsp;There are a TON of useful components, with this being a
list of the ones that I use most often:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://camel.apache.org/bean.html"&gt;Bean&lt;/a&gt; (for calling custom
beans)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://camel.apache.org/file2.html"&gt;File2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://camel.apache.org/jms.html"&gt;JMS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="are-you-a-wizard"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Are you a Wizard?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. &amp;nbsp;But Camel is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It ties together these Endpoints by passing
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://camel.apache.org/maven/current/camel-core/apidocs/org/apache/camel/Message.html"&gt;Messages&lt;/a&gt;
to and fro. &amp;nbsp;In addition to being able to directly configure the
Endpoints, you can manipulate messages en route. &amp;nbsp;For instance, Camel
supports the notion of having &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://camel.apache.org/data-format.html"&gt;Data
Formats&lt;/a&gt; so that it can
seamlessly marshal/unmarshal a message body between Endpoints. &amp;nbsp;An
example use case might be if you're reading an XML file and you want to
call a custom bean that you wrote, passing in the XML as an object.
&amp;nbsp;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://camel.apache.org/jaxb.html"&gt;Camel can use JAXB&lt;/a&gt; to populate
a POJO before calling your bean, preventing your custom bean from having
to know anything about the file itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also handles threading wizardry for you. &amp;nbsp;Many of these components
have multi-thread options, meaning that Camel handles the nasty
threading-bits. &amp;nbsp;It's still incumbent upon the user to make sure that
they're applying parallelism in an appropriate way, but Camel reduces
this exercise to one of configuration and not implementation; Camel's
bits already have this figured out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="bottom-line"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bottom Line?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Camel saved me from having to implement a bunch of custom software to
tie together my systems. &amp;nbsp;I can create an XML config file, a few custom
beans if need be, and presto! &amp;nbsp;I now have Java program that will make
several systems play nice, threading, logging, and all. &amp;nbsp;Camel was a
tremendous find, and it's had a tremendous impact on my work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kudos to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://apache.org"&gt;Apache&lt;/a&gt;, the&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://camel.apache.org"&gt;Camel
project&lt;/a&gt;, and it's leader, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.davsclaus.com/"&gt;Claus
Ibsen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="Apache"></category><category term="Camel"></category><category term="Java"></category></entry><entry><title>Making the (Career) Move</title><link href="http://brianstempin.com/2013/01/12/making-the-career-move/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-01-12T16:06:00-05:00</updated><author><name>bstempi</name></author><id>tag:brianstempin.com,2013-01-12:2013/01/12/making-the-career-move/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've just recently updated &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.linkedin.com/in/brianstempin"&gt;my
LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; to reflect it, but
I left &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.vanguard.com"&gt;Vanguard&lt;/a&gt; back in September to join
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.coldlight.com"&gt;Coldlight Solutions&lt;/a&gt;, a start-up in Wayne,
PA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've not written it here, but those who know me off-line know that I
would like to pursue a PhD at some point in my life. &amp;nbsp;I felt that moving
to Coldlight would put me closer to that goal. &amp;nbsp;Nothing against
Vanguard, but I felt that I wasn't growing that much there. &amp;nbsp;Writing web
services are good and fun, but I was using versions of libraries that
were written for Java 1.4. &amp;nbsp;I wasn't using anything terribly interesting
outside of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.springsource.org/spring-framework"&gt;Spring&lt;/a&gt;.
&amp;nbsp;Unfortunately, Spring isn't the answer to everything. &amp;nbsp;There are bigger
and much more interesting things than Spring in the Java world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coldlight does a lot of work with large data sets and machine learning,
which happens to be a fairly hot research topic. &amp;nbsp;I figured the move
would give me a chance to explore a lot of new technologies and to gain
some experience and insight into a possible PhD research topic. &amp;nbsp;The
move would also have me working with a PhD who could possibly help guide
me into my next transition. &amp;nbsp;After a few rounds of interviewing, I made
the switch: &amp;nbsp;I decided to move to Coldlight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, I've been right. &amp;nbsp;I've learned several new technologies, such as
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://aws.amazon.com/"&gt;Amazon Web Services&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hadoop.apache.org/"&gt;Hadoop&lt;/a&gt;. &amp;nbsp;I've started learning about
different machine learning algorithms by poring through different
implementations and papers. &amp;nbsp;Sure, I occasionally get bogged down in
busy-work and get overloaded. &amp;nbsp;Overall, though, I feel like I've been
growing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an added bonus, I've been able to usher in some practices and
technologies of my own. &amp;nbsp;I've introduced my team to proper SVN usage,
Maven, some pretty cool Eclipse plugins, and a few other things. &amp;nbsp;I'm
directly responsible for some of our process improvement initiatives and
for automating some of our development headaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feels good, man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image0" src="http://brianstempin.com/images/feels-good-man-thumb.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="career"></category></entry><entry><title>How to Move a Wordpress-MU Site to a New Domain</title><link href="http://brianstempin.com/2010/06/07/how-to-move-a-wordpress-mu-site-to-a-new-domai/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-06-07T16:31:00-04:00</updated><author><name>bstempi</name></author><id>tag:brianstempin.com,2010-06-07:2010/06/07/how-to-move-a-wordpress-mu-site-to-a-new-domai/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, as part of my &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.temple.edu/provost/gened"&gt;GenEd&lt;/a&gt; work,
I was asked to move a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mu.wordpress.org/"&gt;WordPress MU&lt;/a&gt;
installation to a new server. &amp;nbsp;I found several articles about moving
around standard WordPress installations, but nothing for the MU
(MultiUser) version. &amp;nbsp;In particular, I had a hard time with changing the
domain name. &amp;nbsp;In this article, I'll assume that you already know the
general procedure (backing up your files and database, moving, and
restoring). &amp;nbsp;All I plan on covering is how to change your installation's
domain name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Make a text backup of your database. &amp;nbsp;You can do this by using
something like
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.1/en/mysqldump.html"&gt;mysqldump&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wiki.phpmyadmin.net/pma/export"&gt;phpMyAdmin&lt;/a&gt;, or the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://downloads.mysql.com/archives.php?p=MySQLGUITools"&gt;MySQL
GUI
Tools&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Using your favorite tool, like notepad,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sed"&gt;sed&lt;/a&gt;, or any other text editor
that can handle large files, replace all instances of your old domain
name with your new one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Save this file and then import it into your database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;In the root of your WordPress MU install, there should be a
wp-config.php file. &amp;nbsp;The majority of this file is a series of DEFINE
statements that define some settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;You should see a like like this:&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p class="first last"&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;define('DOMAIN_CURRENT_SITE',&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;'olddomain.com');&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;
Replace it with:
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;define('DOMAIN_CURRENT_SITE',&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;'newdomain.com');&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;For whatever reason, you'll get a register page if you attempt to
visit your site. &amp;nbsp;To fix this, log in as admin and then log out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Done!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this helps somebody. &amp;nbsp;Feel free to comment if you have questions,
concerns, or corrections.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="GenEd"></category><category term="Guide"></category><category term="WordPress"></category></entry><entry><title>Temple University's General Education Department To Get New Website</title><link href="http://brianstempin.com/2010/05/28/temple-universitys-general-education-department-to-get-new-website/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-05-28T16:18:00-04:00</updated><author><name>bstempi</name></author><id>tag:brianstempin.com,2010-05-28:2010/05/28/temple-universitys-general-education-department-to-get-new-website/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've never mentioned it here before, but for the last 2-ish years, I've
been the webmaster of Temple University's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.temple.edu/gened"&gt;GenEd
website&lt;/a&gt;. &amp;nbsp;The site was originally
developed by Temple University's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.temple.edu/cs"&gt;Computer
Services&lt;/a&gt; group. &amp;nbsp;I took over the
maintenance and have only done small things with it -- add new videos,
replace some files, change text here and there, etc. &amp;nbsp;Nothing too
exciting. &amp;nbsp;Back when I first started, the (then) director of General
Education, Terry Halbert, shared her vision of the website with me. &amp;nbsp;She
envisioned a place where students, faculty, and the community could all
interact. &amp;nbsp;She imagined a place to support and eventually become the
Philadelphia Experience (PEX) Passport (the Passport is a booklet of
discount or free admission tickets to several Philadelphia museums,
venues, and historic sites). &amp;nbsp;She wanted a place that would showcase the
wonderful things that were happening in General Education courses and to
promote the Philadelphia Experience. &amp;nbsp;At the time, I suggested moving to
a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Content_management_system"&gt;CMS&lt;/a&gt; of
some sort, like &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://drupal.org/"&gt;Drupal&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.joomla.org/"&gt;Joomla&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That day has come. &amp;nbsp;GenEd recently received a grant to redesign their
website. &amp;nbsp;As per the&amp;nbsp;recommendation&amp;nbsp;from a few people from the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://community.mis.temple.edu/"&gt;MIS
Department&lt;/a&gt;, which hails from
Temple's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://fox.temple.edu/"&gt;Fox School of Business&lt;/a&gt;, we will be
building a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wordpress.org/"&gt;WordPress&lt;/a&gt; website over the summer
months. &amp;nbsp;The MIS department's website runs WordPress, so they've given
it a very positive recommendation and offered to help with the
implementation. &amp;nbsp;At the moment, we're still nailing down the specs, but
we're hoping to have this completed in time for the incoming class to
see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't say much more other than, &amp;quot;I'm excited!&amp;quot; &amp;nbsp;This will be a big
feather in my cap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;About GenEd:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;At Temple University, we don't have a &amp;quot;core&amp;quot; -- we have GenEd. &amp;nbsp;They
define and develop the classes that students have to take to satisfy
various general education requirements. &amp;nbsp;As a result, this department
in one way or another touches virtually every single student that
comes through our University. &amp;nbsp;In addition to the courses that it
develops, GenEd is also responsible developing the Philadelphia
Experience -- a set of courses and resources to help students take
advantage of and learn from the City of Brotherly Love. &amp;nbsp;They've also
developed the PEX Passport, a collection of free or discounted tickets
that allow students to explore the city for little or no money. &amp;nbsp;This
Passport has also been integrated into some of the classes offered at
Temple and is used to take students outside of the classroom and right
into the environment.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="CMS"></category><category term="GenEd"></category><category term="Temple"></category><category term="web development"></category><category term="WordPress"></category></entry></feed>